Guide to the William S. Vickrey Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - Subseries III.1: Macroeconomics
    - Meaningfully Defining Deficits and Debt, paper, 1991-1992 (Box 14, Folder 236)
      [Paper for session on "Deficits, Which, How Much, and So What?", New Orleans, 4 Jan. 1991. Published in Papers and Proceedings, American Economic Association, May 1992, 305-10. Discusses debt in a Georgist context, varieties of capital budgeting, deficits, unemployment, and growth.]
    - Metastatics and Macroeconomics, bibliography, ca. 1964 (Box 15, Folder 237)
    - Metastatics and Macroeconomics, illustrations, ca. 1964 (Box 15, Folder 238)
    - Metastatics and Macroeconomics, incomplete draft, ca. 1964 (Box 15, Folder 239)
    - Necessary and Optimum Government Debt, paper, March-April 1993 (Box 15, Folder 240)
      [Discusses optimum government normal economy without capital but with money.]
    - Notes on Macroeconomic Instruments, notes, 6 Dec. 1989 (Box 15, Folder 241)
    - Notes on the Macroeconomics of Disarmament, notes (Box 15, Folder 242)
    - One Economists' View of Philanthropy, paper, 1961 (Box 15, Folder 243)
      [Paper for Conference on Philanthropy, Sponsored by National Bureau of Economic Research and Merrill Center for Economics, 26-30 June 1961.]
    - The Other Side of the Coin, address, Sept. 1992 (Box 15, Folder 244)
      [Prepared for an address accepting the Seidman Award, Memphis, 24 Sept. 1992. Subsequently revised and published. Discusses reaching real full employment by vigorous fiscal policy with tradable gross markup warrants as an inflation control.]
    - Review of Disarmament and the Economy, edited by Emile Benoit and Kenneth E. Boulding, book review, 1963 (Box 15, Folder 245)
    - Social Pathologies, Unemployment, and the Fatal Obsession with Debt Reduction and Other Fallacies, paper, 14 July 1994 (Box 15, Folder 246)
    - Some Disastrous Economic Fallacies, notes, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 247)
    - Statement to the Armed Services Subcommittee of the House Appropriations Committee, speech, 17 May 1963 (Box 15, Folder 248)
    - Three Degrees of Separation between Budgets and Reality, paper, 9 March 1996 (Box 15, Folder 249)
    - Today's Task for Economists, address, 1992-1993 (Box 15, Folder 250)
      [Presidential address to the American Economic Association, Jan. 1993. Published in American Economic Review, March 1993, 1-10. Discusses how to raise the economy rapidly to real full employment and keep it there through the use of vigorous public policy and controlling inflation with marketable markup warrants. One draft has comments from Carl Shoup, 17 Nov. 1992.]
    - A Trans-Keynesian Manifesto (Thoughts about an Asset-Based Macro-economics), paper, June-July 1996 (Box 15, Folder 251)
      [A clear statement of views.]
    - Two-Stage Fiscal Program: Stimulus First, Deficit Reduction Second, paper, 1 Nov. 1992 (Box 15, Folder 252)
      [Apparently a preliminary draft of a proposal for the anticipated Clinton Administration.]
    - We Need a Bigger Deficit, paper, Aug-Sept. 1993 (Box 15, Folder 253)
    - We Need Bigger Deficits!, letter to editor (Box 15, Folder 254)
    - What Deficit, Anyhow?, essay (Box 16, Folder 255)
    - Why Balance the Budget?, article, 1959-1960 (Box 16, Folder 256)
      [Published in Challenge.]
    - Why Balance What?, paper, Aug.-Oct. 1995 (Box 16, Folder 257)
    - Why Not Chock-full Employment?, paper, 2 Feb. 1994 (Box 16, Folder 258)
      [Revision of talk to the Atlantic Economic Society, Philadelphia, 1993.]
  - Subseries III.2: Marginal Cost Pricing
    Papers, reviews, articles, statements, essays, and notes about the pricing of natural resources and public utilities. Includes a notebook on postal rate and fee increases as well as his thoughts about efficient pricing, responsive pricing, peak load pricing, tolls and pollution. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Adam and Eve and the Coal Mine: Comments on Harold J. Barnett: "Measurement of Natural Resource Scarcity", review, [1962?] (Box 16, Folder 259)
      [Discusses the pricing of natural resources and the deviations from Hotelling's rule due to changes in expectations, increasing extraction cost, and technological change.]
    - The Airline Booking Problem: Some Further Solutions, paper, Dec. 1970 (Box 16, Folder 260)
      [Published in Journal of Transport Economics and Policy, 6(3), Sept. 1972, 257-70. Discusses pricing on the basis of a simulated futures market and Appendix I estimates the gain from responsive pricing.]
    - Appendix II: Depreciation as an Element of Marginal Cost, paper, 4 Dec. 1990 (Box 16, Folder 261)
    - Apportionment of Cost over Time and Pricing Methods, paper, June 1964 (Box 16, Folder 262)
      [Discusses congestion on electrical networks (power factor) and equipment husbandry.]
    - AT&T Rate Structure Hearings, draft of testimony, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 263)
    - The Backward Art of Utility Pricing, paper, Aug. 1988 (Box 16, Folder 264)
      [Discussion Paper Series No. 404, Columbia University, August 1988. Discusses responsive pricing, power factor charges, lifeline rates, and subsidy from land taxation.]
    - Decreasing Costs, Publicly Administered Prices, and Economic Efficiency, paper, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 265)
      [Background paper for the Joint Economic Committee Study of "Economic Analysis of Public Expenditure: The PPB System." Discusses marginal cost pricing, subsidies, and the excess burden of taxation in the context of the "Program, Planning and Policy Budgeting System."]
    - Economic Efficiency and Pricing, paper, 1970-1971 (Box 16, Folder 266)
      [Published in Public Prices for Public Products. Edited by Selma J. Mushkin. Washington: Urban Institute, 1972.]
    - Economies of Scale Stemming from Indivisibilities, paper, 28 June 1969 (Box 16, Folder 267)
    - Economizing and Pricing of Computer Services, paper, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 268)
      [Concerns batch processing.]
    - Efficient Pricing and its Impact on Operating Costs, Fuel Requirements, Capacity Expansion, Retirement of Obsolete Plants, and Integration of Exotic Power Schedules, essay, 28 March 1980 (Box 16, Folder 269)
      [Offers responsive pricing as an option to standard pricing.]
    - Efficient Pricing of Electric Power Service: Some Innovative Solutions, paper, 1990-1992 (Box 17, Folder 270)
      [Published in Resources and Energy, 14, 1992, 157-74. Discusses responsive pricing, power factor, formulation of subsidies, pricing of hydro power, and second-best considerations. ]
    - Efficient Pricing under Regulation: The Case of Responsive Pricing as a Substitute for Interruptible Power Contracts, paper, June 1978 (Box 17, Folder 271)
      [Draft for Proceedings: Marginal Costing and Pricing of Electrical Energy, Canadian Electrical Association with Canadian Bureau of Mines and Resources, Canada, 1-4 May 1978, pp. 38-58. See also Notes on Interruptible Power and Alternative Pricing Methods, Box 17, Folder 286.]
    - Efficient Pricing vs. Privatization of Utility Services, paper, Nov. 1991 (Box 17, Folder 272)
      [Prepared for a meeting on Argentina, Waldorf Astoria Hotel, New York, 18-19 November 1991. Discusses that varying fare by time of day encourages staggered work hours and makes the point that making toll voluntary (or allowing people to wait in a lay-by) results in everyone being made better off by tolling a bottleneck.]
    - Hotel Problem, notes (Box 17, Folder 273)
      [Discusses responsive pricing.]
    - Interrelations between Interest Rates and Depreciation Rates, paper, 1970-1971 (Box 17, Folder 274)
      [Published in Utility Regulation During Inflation. Edited by J. E. Haring and J. F. Humphrey. Glendale, California: Occidental College, 1971. Discusses the dangers of front-end loading of costs and double counting in inflationary circumstances.]
    - Investment Bias under Regulatory Constraint, paper, Sept. 1965 (Box 17, Folder 275)
      [Paper prepared for presentation at the Symposium on Economics of Public Utilities, Airlie House, Warrenton, Va., 7-10 Sept. 1965]
    - IPA Water Outlines, notes, 1969, undated (Box 17, Folder 276)
    - Local Telephone Costs and the Design of Rate Structures: An Innovative View, paper, March 1981 (Box 17, Folder 277)
      [Discusses responsive pricing and land taxes.]
    - Marginal Cost Pricing: Using the Short Run for the Long Run, article, 1983 (Box 17, Folder 278)
      [An abbreviated version of this article was presented at the meetings of the Eastern Economic Association, Boston, 11 March 1983.]
    - Maximum Output or Maximum Welfare? More on the Off-Peak Pricing Problem, article, Dec. 1970 (Box 17, Folder 279)
      [Published in Kyklow, 24(2), 1971, 305-29. Includes critique of a naive proposal for determining peak price differentials.]
    - The Meaning of Marginal Cost: Some New (Empty?) Boxes for Old, paper (Box 17, Folder 280)
      [Discusses short- and long-run relevant product mines, queuing, travel time, schedule delay, relevance to direct controls, bottleneck model, and marginal cost pricing.]
    - Measurement of Demand for Demand Changes, fragment (Box 17, Folder 281)
    - New Approaches to Marginal Cost Pricing of Electricity, notes, [1990] (Box 17, Folder 282)
      [Notes for a talk at Lehigh University, 17 February [1990].]
    - Notes and Amendments regarding the Proposed City Club statement: "A New York City Energy Policy for the Eighties", review, 1980 (Box 17, Folder 283)
      [Argues for time-of-day-pricing in New York City.]
    - Notes on AT&T Testimony, notes, 1965 & 1968 (Box 17, Folder 284)
    - Notes on Brancato: Criteria for Redesigning Rates, review, April 1974 (Box 17, Folder 285)
    - Notes on Interruptible Power and Alternative Pricing Methods, notes, 6 April 1977 (Box 17, Folder 286)
      [See also Efficient Pricing Under Regulation: The Case of Responsive Pricing as a Substitute for Interruptible Power Contracts, Box 17, Folder 271.]
    - Notes on Statements to the FCC, notes, July-Oct. 1968 (Box 17, Folder 287)
    - Notes on the Con Ed Crisis, fragment (Box 17, Folder 288)
    - Notes on Welfare Economics as a Theory of Teams, notes (Box 17, Folder 289)
    - Notes re: Marginal Cost Pricing, notes (Box 18, Folder 290)
    - Optimal Electricity Prices, draft of chapter 3 (Box 18, Folder 291)
    - Optimum Allocation of Intra-Marginal Residues, paper (Box 18, Folder 292)
      [Discusses Ramsey pricing for public utilities.]
    - Postal Rate and Fee Increases Notebook, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 293)
      [Notebook is related to Vickrey's role as witness in Docket No. RT4-1 regarding postal rate and fee increases.]
    - Postal Rate and Fee Increases Notebook: Memos, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 294)
    - Postal Rate and Fee Increases Notebook: Direct Testimony and Exhibits, 1973 (Box 18, Folder 295)
    - Postal Rate and Fee Increases Notebook: Interrogations and Answers by Party, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 296)
    - Postal Rate and Fee Increases Notebook: Written Cross Examinations, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 297)
    - Postal Rate and Fee Increases Notebook: Motions, 1973-1974 (Box 18, Folder 298)
    - Postal Rate and Fee Increases Notebook: Rebuttal Testimony, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 299)
    - Postal Rate Structure, notes (Box 18, Folder 300)
    - Pricing for Tomorrow: The Welfare Economics of Price Structures Adapted to an Electronic Age, drafts (Box 18, Folder 301)
      [Incomplete manuscript of a book in years of gestation.]
    - Pricing for Tomorrow: The Welfare Economics of Price Structures Adapted to an Electronic Age, fragments (Box 19, Folder 302)
    - The Pricing of Tomorrow's Utility Services, paper, 1968 (Box 19, Folder 303)
      [Published in The New Economics of Regulated Industries: Rate-Making in a Dynamic Economy. Edited by Joseph E. Haring. Los Angeles Economics Research Center, Occidental College, 1968.]
    - Rebuttal by Vickrey, transcript, 1974 (Box 19, Folder 304)
      [Postal Rate Commission testimony on the pricing and cost services of postal service. Vickrey argues for Ramsey pricing, discusses the economics of scale in postal service, and gives definition of marginal cost.]
    - Remarks at Institute of Public Utilities Conference, speech, May 1975 (Box 19, Folder 305)
    - Responsive Pricing and Homeostatic Control, paper, May 1979 (Box 19, Folder 306)
      [Discusses responsive pricing for electricity.]
    - Responsive Pricing Based on Marginal Cost as a Means of Promoting Efficient Energy Usage, paper, June 1979 (Box 19, Folder 307)
      [Paper for the IAEE-RFF Conference on International Energy Issues, Sheraton Park Hotel, Washington, D.C., 4-6 June 1979. Published in International Energy Strategies. Proceedings of the 1978 International Association of Energy Economics. Edited by James Duesenberry. See also International Association of Energy Economists (IAEE) Annual Conference, Box 41, Folder 699.]
    - Responsive Pricing of Public Utility Services, paper, 1970 (Box 19, Folder 308)
      [Published in Economics of the Regulated Communications Industry in the Age of Innovation, 1970 Seminar, New England Telephone, pp. 61-8. Discusses the original suggestion for implementing short-run marginal-cost pricing in terms of separating flexible consumer payment rates set freely by the utility from utility retention rates set by regulatory procedures, with an escrow fund to absorb differences. Also has suggestion for low-cost metering technology.]
    - Statement at the Public Hearing held by the Department of Environmental Conservation regarding Mobile Pollutants, statement, 24 Jan. 1979 (Box 19, Folder 309)
      [The hearing was held in County Center, White Plains, New York, 24 Jan. 1979. Discusses tolling as a way to reduce pollution.]
    - Statement before Water Resources Subcommittee of U.S. Senate Committee on Public Works, statement, 1 April 1977 (Box 19, Folder 310)
      [The statement concerns user charges on inland waterways and competition with railroads.]
    - Statement to New York State Assembly Standing Committee on Corporations, Authorities, and Commissions, statement, 24 Sept. 1975 (Box 19, Folder 311)
      [Discusses lifeline pricing of telephone service to the poor.]
    - Tarifacion de Pasajes, Por Avion, Tema No. 9, lecture notes, 15 July 1976, (langcode="spa">Spanish) (Box 19, Folder 312)
    - Tarifacion en Los Muelles, Tema No. 10, lecture notes, 15 July 1976, (langcode="spa">Spanish) (Box 19, Folder 313)
    - La Tarification des Communications Urbains: Principes Economiques, Possibilites Techiques, Resultats Pratiques, paper, Nov. 1973, (langcode="spa">Spanish) (Box 19, Folder 314)
      [Presented in Barcelona]
    - Teoria del Segundo Mejor (second best), Tema No. 11, lecture notes, 16 July 1976, (langcode="spa">Spanish) (Box 19, Folder 315)
    - Testimony before the Environmental Defense Fund, transcript (Box 19, Folder 316)
      [Discusses marginal cost pricing of public utilities.]
    - Testimony before the Federal Communications Commission, in relation to Charges for Program Transmission Services Rendered by the Bell System to the Radio and Television Networks, draft, 1967 (Box 19, Folder 317)
      [Discusses telephone pricing.]
    - Testimony before the New York Public Service Commission in behalf of the Environmental Defense Fund in the matter of Niagara-Mohawk Power Corporation Electric Rates, Case 26402, transcript, 27 July 1973 (Box 19, Folder 318)
      [The testimony argues for peak-load pricing and time-of-day metering, describes possible technologies, and provides definitions of marginal cost and Ramsey pricing.]
    - Theoretical and Practical Possibilities and Limitations of a Market Mechanism Approach to Air Pollution Control, article, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 319)
      [Listed as forthcoming, Land Economics, Feb. 1992.]
  - Subseries III.3: Microeconomics
    Primarily outline, illustrations, bibliography, appendices, errata, and notes for Vickrey's graduate level textbook Microstatics published in 1964. Also includes his review of "The Taxation of Income from Capital." Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Notes on The Taxation of Income from Capital, review, Feb. 1983 (Box 20, Folder 320)
    - Microstatics, bibliography, ca. 1964 (Box 20, Folder 321)
      [A graduate level textbook. Reprinted once and contains some errors.]
    - Microstatics, errata, ca. 1964 (Box 20, Folder 322)
    - Microstatics, illustrations, ca. 1964 (Box 20, Folder 323)
    - Microstatics, mathematical appendices, ca. 1964 (Box 20, Folder 324)
    - Microstatics, notes, ca. 1964 (Box 20, Folder 325)
    - Microstatics, outline, ca. 1964 (Box 20, Folder 326)
  - Subseries III.4: Political Economy and Welfare
    Papers, book reviews, and an outline of remarks on the subjects of social science, world development, poverty, and corporate giving. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - America's Capability for Tooling Up World Development, paper, undated (Box 20, Folder 327)
    - Auschwitz--and Hiroshima, paper, 3 Oct. 1958 (Box 20, Folder 328)
    - Book Review of Economic Factors in the Growth of Corporation Giving by Ralph L. Nelson, book review, 1971 (Box 20, Folder 329)
      [Published in Journal of Economic Literature.]
    - Comments on Essays in the Structure of Social Science Models by Albert Ando, Franklin M. Fisher, and Herbert A. Simon, book review, 1964 (Box 20, Folder 330)
    - Maldistribution of Wealth: Provision for Each Individual within the National Economy, outline, 28 Oct. 1969 (Box 20, Folder 331)
      [Outline of remarks prepared for delivery to the Institute for Religion and Social Studies, 26 Oct. 1969. Discusses the fairly drastic measures required for eliminating poverty by redistribution.]
  - Subseries III.5: Public Finance
    A paper on tax cuts, a book review concerning taxation, and notes regarding land tax and how tax policies encourage investment. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Cut the Corporate Income Tax, not Capital Gains, paper, undated (Box 20, Folder 332)
    - Notes on the Land Tax, notes (Box 20, Folder 333)
      [Discusses the lack of neutrality of market value less depreciated improvementsapproach.]
    - Review of The Economics of Taxation by Henry Aaron and Michael J. Boskins, eds., book review, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 334)
      [Comments on averaging.]
    - Tax and Other Policies to Encourage Investment, notes, Aug. 1993 (Box 20, Folder 335)
      [Notes for a discussion oat Great Barrington, 19-21 Aug. 1993. Discusses cumulative averaging and categorization of types of investment.]
  - Subseries III.6: Social Choice
    Papers, reviews, and notes about social choice and welfare. Topics addressed include auctions, game theory, demand revealing procedures, equity, justice, and related societal issues. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Agenda Setting and Social Choice, paper, June 1980 (Box 20, Folder 336)
      [Published in Public Transfers and Some Private Alternatives During the Recession. Schriften des Internationalen Institute fur Empirische Sozialokonomie, Band 7(II). Edited by Martin Pfaff. Berlin: Duncker & Humblot, 1983. Discusses the power of an agenda setter in social choice procedures and methods of avoiding such bias.]
    - An Anonymity-Preserving Procedure for Sealed Bid Auctions, paper, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 337)
    - The Arrow Social Choice Theorem, paper (Box 20, Folder 338)
    - Auctions and Bidding Games, paper, 1962 (Box 21, Folder 339)
      [Published in Recent Advances in Game Theory, The Princeton University Conference, 1962, 15-27. Includes further mathematical analysis of various types of auctions in terms of game theory and in relation to Pareto efficiency.]
    - Auctions, Markets, and Optimal Allocation, paper, 1974-1976 (Box 21, Folder 340)
      [Published in Bidding and Auctioning for Procurement and Allocation. Studies in Game Theory and Mathematical Economics. Edited by Yakow Amihud. New York University Press, 1976. Previously presented at a conference at NYU in 1974. Contains non-mathematical overview and notes.]
    - Bidding Procedures and Economic Efficiency, paper, April 1980 (Box 21, Folder 341)
    - A Comment on Tideman and Tullock's "A New and Superior Process for Making Social Choice", review, Jan. 1976 (Box 21, Folder 342)
    - Demand Revealing Procedures, Collusion, and Lump-sum Payments, paper, 1976 (Box 21, Folder 343)
      [Discusses the ways of dealing with problems that arise in various contexts and includes a bibliography.]
    - Demand Revealing Procedures for Public Choice: Beyond Majority Rule, paper, June 1994 (Box 21, Folder 344)
    - Demand Revealing Procedures in International Disputes, paper, Nov. 1979 (Box 21, Folder 345)
    - Demand Revealing Procedures in International Disputes, paper, 14 May 1992 (Box 21, Folder 346)
    - A Further Simplification of Consumer's Surplus, paper (Box 21, Folder 347)
      [Argues that compensating variation likely to be used in practice rather than equivalent valuation.]
    - The Intensity Problem: A Perennially Elusive Target, paper (Box 21, Folder 348)
    - Justice, Bloomberg, etc., notes (Box 21, Folder 349)
      [Possibly notes for lecture.]
    - Justice, Economics, and Jurisprudence, article, 1976-1977 (Box 21, Folder 350)
      [Published in Social Research, 46(2), 1979, 272-81. Discusses the concepts of equity, and how especially naive concepts can be in sharp conflict with economic efficiency.]
    - Lifeline Rates: Succor or Snare?, paper (Box 21, Folder 351)
      [Discusses the role of equity in public utility pricing.]
    - Myopia, Consistency, and Exponential Discounting, paper, 1957-1966 (Box 21, Folder 352)
      [Drafts accompanied by pages of algebra, correspondence, and copy of "How Income Ought to be Distributed: A Paradox in Distributive Ethics" by Robert H. Strotz.]
    - Preference, Probability, and Proficiency, paper (Box 21, Folder 353)
    - Review of Collective Choice and Social Welfare by Amartya K. Sen, book review (Box 21, Folder 354)
    - Risk, Utility, and Social Policy, paper, 1961 (Box 21, Folder 355)
      [Defends expected utility as measure of satisfaction.]
    - The Weltanschauung of an Economist, paper (Box 21, Folder 356)
      [Discusses Rawls, Nozick, and equity in economics.]
  - Subseries III.7: Taxation
    Papers, notes, articles, and reviews concerning the effects of taxation on the economy. These papers include examination of the simplification of the tax system, tax revenues, capital gains, progressive taxation, land value taxation, tax evasion, assessments, philanthropy, tax credits, income, and related issues. Also discusses federal income tax, international tax, corporate income tax, state taxes, excise tax, expenditures tax, estate taxes, and gift taxes. Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Alternatives to the International Tax Credit, paper, Aug. 1978 (Box 21, Folder 357)
    - Alternatives to the International Tax Credit--Some Afterthoughts, paper, 26 Oct. 1978 (Box 21, Folder 358)
    - Comments on Jennifer Arlen and Deborah Weiss's A Political Theory of Corporate Taxation, book review (Box 21, Folder 359)
    - Concession Agreements: Liberia, paper, 1968-1969 (Box 21, Folder 360)
      [Discusses the economics of concessions.]
    - The Consequences of the Corporation Income Tax: A Macroeconomic Approach, paper (Box 22, Folder 361)
    - The Corporate Income Tax and How to Get Rid of It, paper, May 1989 (Box 22, Folder 362)
      [Published in Retrospective on Public Finance. Edited by Loraine Eden. Duke University Press, 1991. Discusses the tax's effects on the economy, political popularity incidence in relation to macroeconomic policy, replacement with withholding tax, cumulative assessment, regression-based allocation of income by source, and the replacement of the foreign tax credit.]